<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Better late than never</title>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1689</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 20 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 3 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2012-10">2012-10 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A27550</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing B2083</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R23548</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">12072528</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 12072528</idno>
            <idno type="VID">53512</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A27550)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 53512)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 858:8)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>Better late than never</title>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[4] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>s.n.,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>[S.l. :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1689]</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in Huntington Library.</note>
                  <note>Caption title.</note>
                  <note>Written in defense of James II and warns of the rise of arbitrary government and the loss of ancient priviledges.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>James --  II, --  King of England, 1633-1701.</term>
               <term>England and Wales. --  Sovereign (1685-1688 : James II)</term>
               <term>Great Britain --  History --  1660-1714.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2009-04</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-05</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-02</date>
            <label>Judith Siefring</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-02</date>
            <label>Judith Siefring</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-05</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb facs="tcp:53512:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <head>Better Late than Never.</head>
            <p>IT is melancholly to conſider in what a con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dition theſe poor Kingdoms are; and that which makes it ſtill more deplorable is, that they have, in a great meaſure, been brought to this languiſhing State by thoſe who really wiſh their Countrey's Good; and that even thoſe are ſtill the men that moſt endanger the Liberty and Property, about which they have ſo inceſſantly ſtrove: For whether King <hi>James,</hi> or K. <hi>William</hi> prevails, all our ancient Privileges ſeem expiring; and we are threatened, on all ſides, with Milita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry and Arbitrary Government, unleſs we make a Tender of the Crown upon the Terms of the Conſtitution, to the King we have hi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>therto <hi>Abdicated,</hi> and who cannot, in com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon Honeſty, and according to the genuine ſignification of the Word, be ſaid to have ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dicated his Crown, till he refuſes it upon thoſe Terms; which if he ſhould, the Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtinction of His and the <hi>Williamite</hi> Party would ſoon have an End, and we ſhould all join againſt <hi>Him</hi> and <hi>France,</hi> as common <hi>Foes,</hi> and fight <hi>pro Aris &amp; Focis</hi> to the ut<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moſt Extremity, and with that united Reſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lution, that Religion and neceſſity inſpire. I do in my Conſcience believe, there are not in <hi>England</hi> ſo ſenſible and worthy Men as thoſe who frequent the <hi>Roſe,</hi> and <hi>Richard</hi>'s, and their Friends, and yet notwithſtanding their <hi>Honeſty</hi> is not to be corrupted, and their <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nderſtandings</hi> are ſo acute and remar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king, their <hi>Tempers</hi> have been fatally violent, and rather apt to pull down than to build up, and carried away with perſonal Piques and Prepoſſeſſion: ſometimes they are too refi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned <hi>Platoniſts,</hi> too <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>topian;</hi> and at other <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>eaſons they know no bounds of Law, where a point of Intereſt requires laying it aſide; <hi>they,</hi> as well as others, can <hi>ſtrain</hi> the Conſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tution till it cracks. I have a true value for many of that Company, and could they pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiently in private examine theſe Subjects, would beg ſuch a Converſation, for I dare truſt their Honour; but ſeeing too much heat remains among them to hope for that, am deſirous to offer ſome things to their Conſideration.</p>
            <p>I will not entertain them with what may be obſerved from the late Times; but I be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieve they will find many true Engliſhmen oppoſed the Lengths the <hi>Army</hi> went. I am ſure brave <hi>Algernoon Sidney</hi> did for one. I would onely offer this one thing here, which they may apply to every part of my Diſcourſe, where it is needfull, and that is, (let it be true or falſe,) <hi>That Succeſive Monarchy is the Government of</hi> England. So many are of that Belief and Humour, That he that has that <hi>Title,</hi> will never want a <hi>conſiderable Party,</hi> though thoſe very Engliſhmen will be very ſenſible when their <hi>Religion</hi> and <hi>Properties</hi> are invaded.</p>
            <p>Give me leave, from hence, to repreſent the Dangers into which you were formerly driving the Nation, when the <hi>Bill of Excluſion</hi> was on foot, and what Advantages you might have had, if your hatred to the then Duke of <hi>York</hi> had not overthrown your Judgment, and perfectly miſled you; or, next this late Advantage, no Party could have wiſhed for a fairer Opportunity, than that was to gain their Point, which, but too plainly told us, the Quarrel was more <hi>Perſonal</hi> than <hi>National,</hi> that they had more averſion to him than love to their Country. If that Bill had paſſed, you know many would not have ſet down by it, and you had had every Body upon your Back from abroad; and what was yet more than I believe many of you then knew or feared, even this preſent King too, who of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fered to ſerve his Father-in-law againſt the Duke of <hi>Monmouth, and gave him Intelligence,</hi> as well as ſent him over the Regiments. But, on the other ſide, if <hi>Expedients</hi> would have ſerved your Turn, you might have ſerved your ſelves of the Humour of the Reguant Prince, who though he was wiſe, yet loved his Pleaſure and his Eaſe, and was of a timo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rous Nature; ſo that whatever might be his Inclinations towards his Brother, he was not for ſuch bold ſteps in Government; yet ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther than hazard a Rebellion, he would have parted with as much of what Flatterers had called <hi>Prerogative,</hi> as ſhould have made your Li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>berties ſafe under all ſucceeding Kings; but you were too warm at that Day to hear of any thing like this. Thus <hi>Plato Redivivus</hi> was a Popiſh Author, <hi>The preſent Intereſt of</hi> Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land writ by a Jeſuite, and Mr. <hi>Sacheverill</hi> (that true old Engliſh-man, who alters not his Judgment for his own, and leſs for any
<pb facs="tcp:53512:2"/>other Man's Paſſion) ſcarce regarded, when he ſpoke, in the Houſe of Commons; and to be for the Bill of <hi>Excluſion</hi> was the diſtinc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tive Badg of an honeſt Man, as if we were to be preſerved by the Religion of our Kings, rather than by the Conſtitution of our Govern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, an Errour as great as dangerous: ſince all our Safety would lie upon the Stability of his Opinion, that might be as ſoon influen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ced as another Man's; and not upon the Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture and Efficacy of our Laws: I indeed expected more diſmal Broils to have been the Conſequences of theſe Heats; and yet what happened deſerves to be lamented. The next thing wherein your Paſſion miſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led you, was your Tumultuous Oppoſition to the taking off the <hi>Penal Laws and Teſts.</hi> Li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>berty of Conſcience uſed to be your Inclina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, as well as it was King <hi>James</hi> his Intereſt; and when he went about to introduce it irre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gularly, you ſhould have had the Bravery to have told him, that you were not now more than formerly againſt <hi>Liberty of Conſcience;</hi> but that you would be againſt 'it, if it was to undermine the Liberties of your Country, and to ſhew you meant no more, if he did not, you were ready to joyn Iſſue and oblige him, and that you were neither Implacable nor Inſatiable. You ſhould have had ſo much Morality and good Senſe, as to let the Papiſts ſee you would let them have the Priviledges of Engliſh-men, if they would be ſuch in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deed, and not flatter an Intereſt againſt the Conſtitution, but be true to it, and be only upon an equal Ballance, and preferred in pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>portion to their Numbers. Had he or they ſlighted, or uſed you ill for this Offer, you had been juſtified before all Mankind in all you did before this Revolution; and what you have done ſince would be eaſily excuſed and palliated upon grounds of Polity. But, pray, let me Expoſtulate with you here; Why were you ſo zealous to over-look the <hi>Prince of</hi> Orange <hi>his Declaration,</hi> and ſet him up for King? Why would you let the Scotch appear ſo much a more reaſonable and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolute People for their Freedoms? Why were you not more Explanatory about your <hi>New Original Contract?</hi> Why were you more fixed upon changing Perſons, than regardful of Things? I believe, at this Day, you wiſh you had been wiſer: I am ſure I do. I think it the greateſt Advantage loſt, that perhaps the Nation ever had, and to tell you true, the only pretence and excuſe you could have for what you have done, and the Nation has ſuffered. Thoſe that were for the Regency were come to their Wits, and did not any longer think <hi>Abſolute Power Jure Divino,</hi> or the beſt Model, and would have heartily joyned with you in ſettling the Nation; though I am not ſure, and I believe you are as little, that they will to the <hi>laſt Drop and Farthing ſupport what you have done.</hi> I thought it an infinite Mercy that the Miſcarriages of the late Reigns had at laſt ſo opened their Eyes, but you your ſelves ſeem to be dimmer ſighted in Proſperity. When the <hi>Popiſh-Plot</hi> gave you Power to carry the <hi>Mobb</hi> at your Heels, you were for carrying the World be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore you, and nothing would ſerve your turns, but carrying it too in your own way: But after the <hi>Oxford Parliament</hi> was Diſſolv'd, you found you had been in the wrong; and after the defeat of the <hi>Duke of Monmouth</hi> were more convinced of it, though had he Succeeded, and his Title been examined and al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowed in Parliament, I beleive we ſhould have been more unanimous than we are now; but his <hi>Taunton Proclamation</hi> deſerved and haſten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed his Ruine, and would have leſſened his Party, if <hi>King James</hi> his Miniſters had made right uſe of it; and in this Revolution with <hi>Captain Tom</hi>'s Troops, you ſcorn'd any thing leſs than <hi>Elective Monarchy.</hi> The People are not ſo Nice as to underſtand the Diſpute, but Time will ſhew their ſenſibility of <hi>Taxes</hi> and <hi>Poverty,</hi> and when they repent too late, <hi>You will do ſo too.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>If you could take a ſedate Account of Things, with reſpect to the Humours of Men, and the Intereſts of other Countries, and how they regard us, and we them, in order to a true Judgment, what is fit to be done upon preſent Accidents, how change of Affairs varies Intereſts, you would not be ſo often out in your Reckoning; but your Specula<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions truſt a little too much to the preſent Strength of your own Country Beef and Beer, and to the Confidence your honeſt Meaning makes your Country-men place in you. You are admirable in ſudden Reflections and Ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſervations upon home Politicks; but few of you are very general; and if a Man reaſons right upon foreign Affairs that regard us, you ſuſpect him ſcarce true to your Party; and you are never willing to yield either to the neceſſity of Things, or to better Arguments than you did firſt think of. You have a little too much of the <hi>Modern Italianiſm,</hi> rather than
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:53512:3"/>the greatneſs of the <hi>Old Roman.</hi> Thus every little thing you miſlike in any man, throws you into extremeſt Jealouſie and Diſguſt, with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out examining how uprightly he has acted in that wherein you challenge him; you think a Man wants Principle, who ſteps in any one thing out of your Road, and the Opinions that are then in Vogue amongſt you, and that has any acquaintance that you don't under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtand, though never ſo deſerving. This is a ſort of Popery in Government: For you prefer old Forms and Traditions before In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quiry and Truth. Intereſts change and ſort themſelves afreſh; and an Ignorance of that, or a prejudice againſt them that ſhew it, will make you miſs your Mark, do what you can. It would be happier for you, and your Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trey too, if you were leſs Captious, and kept a better and freer Correſpondence. There are in all Intereſts thoſe that would ſerve you Faithfully, and will never ſerve any Body but upon your Bottom. I am confident if you would have been cool, you might have had Accounts worth your Knowledge, and been able to judge of Futurities. Enquire well into the Lives as well as Characters of Men, and ſee whether they have juſtly forfeited your Eſteem, and believe not too unchari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tably; and above all, loſe not any Oppor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tunity of being acquainted with the ſtate of Things abroad: Perhaps you have loſt good ones, of having been early informed to <hi>Europe,</hi> of Princes <hi>Courts,</hi> of their Inclinations and Motions too. Can't you examine Things, and do afterwards as you your ſelves think moſt Adviſable? Whilſt I write thus to you, perhaps I am too much in the Dark my ſelf; but could I ſee you growing capable of ſuch Debates, I queſtion not but that you might fall into Methods more likely, and more ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tional than thoſe, that only preſerve ſuch Men as you lately hated; and to give them an Opportunity to ſecure themſelves at your Hazard. If you will be true to your own Principles, you muſt miſlike Miſmanagement as well in one Man as another, and that will prove to the World, that it is not perſonal Love or Averſion that governs you; and if a Revolution comes, it ſets you as fair for Grace and Favour, as the Miniſters of State them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves, unleſs they do ſome very great Thing to deſerve more; but, perhaps, their not being ſo ſullen to <hi>Jacobites</hi> may teach 'em the Compaſs better. Nay, it will prove to this very King that you are not Aſſes made for Burthen, nor wholly to be neglected, ei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther in your Counſels, or your Perſons: He would quickly ſee the <hi>Whiggs</hi> made him King, and that their Intereſt is neceſſary to ſupport his Throne; and that you denied his Power of Stamping the worſt Men, before they were well melted down and refined into Saints. Thus you would have it in your Power to ſupport this Government; or if K. <hi>W.</hi> contribute to his own Deſtruction, you will have diſcharged your ſelves like Men of Senſe, and Lovers of your Country; and be received like Men of Honour, and not deſtroyed for Perſons irrecon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cilable and ill-natured.</p>
            <p>To give King <hi>James</hi> but his Due, he made ſome Overtures of coming towards your Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty; and is the only King has made any ſince the Reſtoration, and long before too: And it can't be ſtrange, that ſince your Politicks have been ſo little <hi>Alamode</hi> of late, he ſhould miſtake in his Applications to you: But two things put you and him at vaſter diſtance<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> Some of the Diſſenters were ſo agog with Liberty, and ſome of them ſo deſirous to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venge themſelves upon the <hi>Church</hi> of <hi>England,</hi> that they thought no Flatteries too great for an Addreſs; and on the other ſide, you that were the <hi>State-Whiggs,</hi> inſtead of appearing at <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap>, to direct and govern his Approaches to you, (the thing of the World which would have pleas'd him the beſt, and which ſome of you were invited to) and, in a bare-faced manner, publiſhing your Notions of Govern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, you unfairly betook your ſelves to <hi>Libels;</hi> and an <hi>avow'd Sullenneſs,</hi> that made that King believe you would be <hi>Male-Contents</hi> under any Adminiſtration; at leaſt, that it was impoſſible for him to ſatisfie you: And there were ſome <hi>Church-Favourites</hi> about that King, who are not more your Friends a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bout this, who were ready to give every thing that Turn. Inſtead of making your Advan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tage of that Coldneſs that grew between Him and the <hi>High Church,</hi> and ſtepping in between them, and managing that happy Juncture to all thoſe glorious Ends you had long flatter'd your ſelves with, and which his Neceſſities, and thoſe of his Party (too inconſiderable to hazard you) would, with a tolerable Addreſs, have brought him to; you moſt unfortunately danced to their Pipe that had been deaf to all your Charms, hated your Principles, and had waſhed their Hands, but a little before, in the Blood of your Friends, and with them overthrew that King, in hopes by making to
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:53512:3" rendition="simple:additions"/>have got and kept another to your ſelves, who convinces you every day, he does not love your Perſons, and is affraid of your Prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciples. Reflexions on theſe Errour<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> may be of ſome uſe to you now, when Things ſeem to look as if we were not at an End of our <hi>Changes.</hi> Be not deceived therefore again, and let not Names fright you. It is a dan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gerous Civil Superſtition you have too long abuſed your ſelves with. I ſhould think what you have done and undone, given and paid, ſuffered, and are like to ſuffer, by <hi>Taxes, Affronts,</hi> and <hi>Diſappointments,</hi> ſhould perfectly cure you of <hi>Traditional-Hates,</hi> and make you examine carefully, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>f<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> King <hi>JAMES</hi> has all that real Miſchief and Terror in him, by the Inſinuations of which you have long govern'd the <hi>Mobb</hi> againſt him: If you have not, at laſt, given away, where it may be too ſtrong for you, when you <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>ed it for your ſelves, or thoſe from whom <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ou may have fairer Quarter. Whether we <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>egard his Humour, his Age, his Intereſt; after what he has ſeen, ſuffered, and yet fears, methinks he cannot be ſo terrible to us.</p>
            <p>To this add the Minority of his Son, and the Inconſiderableneſs of his Party, and that he muſt of neceſſity, to preſerve both, allow us a better <hi>Bargain</hi> than we <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap> any body elſe: Think alſo with your ſelves, if he deſires to be a <hi>Tributary Prince,</hi> or to be reſtored to a waſted Country; or if it be poſſible he ſhould be reſtored before it be ſo, unleſs it be with the Conſent of his People; and whether it be not your great Intereſt to haſten it, before <hi>France</hi> be at leiſure to do it in a way not agreeable to him or you. It is too advent'rous and ſanguine, in my Opinion, to put all into the Power of ſuch an Accident. If you think of it quickly you prevent the French King, and oblige him to conſent to his Return: but if you are obſtinate, perhaps, he has the means of continuing the War till you can no longer reſiſt; and then you are to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceive Terms inſtead of giving them. And though King <hi>James</hi> were out of the Queſtion, it is your Intereſt to prevent this; but he is the next and Infallible Means of doing it, as you may manage the Buſineſs. He muſt be a wiſe and unskilful Mariner that will never weigh Anchor but when he can ſaid before the Wind. Improve all the Opportunities that offer themſelves to you, to the Noble End you aim at; and henceforward overlook none; nor miſtake any. Let your Thoughts be as large as your Subject, freed of the Biaſs, a narrow Education and Home-ſpun Prejudice, are apt to give them. This muſt be allowed to be one of the moſt incurable Diſtempers our Natures ſuffer under; but where there is ſo great a ſtock of good Senſe already, as you are Maſters of, our preſent great Miſeries muſt enlighten you<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> And to be yet freer with you, ſince our Fears are of <hi>France,</hi> (and not with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out Cauſe, as the matter has been managed) I muſt cell you that there are things to be ga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thered out of the knowledg of the preſent King of <hi>France</hi> his Temper and Affairs, from which you might draw Concluſions of more Security and Benefit than you are aware of, and all your Obſtinacy will give you.</p>
            <p>But it you will rail on, without conſidering whether you can have any Remedy againſt your Fears, and overlook thoſe that offer themſelves, you are of an unfortunate Diſpo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſition. If there is no way for you to under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtand theſe things, you lie under unhappy Circumſtances. If I might adviſe, you ſhould not mix ſo much Paſſion with your Diſcour<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes; but ſhould caſt about, whether ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing, very probable, has not lately appear'd, to let you into juſter Obſervations: And be likewiſe aſſur'd, that ſo long as you continue moroſe, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap> and chooſe to be deſtroy'd <hi>rather than ſaved againſt your Prejudices;</hi> every Body will be afraid to tell his Tale to you, though it be never ſo true and good a one: So that you will be the laſt left to maintain <hi>That,</hi> which yet will deſtroy you if it ſtands, and be marked as the moſt Inveterate Enemies of <hi>Succeſſive Monarchy,</hi> though you might have it within your own Bounds; to which that very part of the Church of <hi>England</hi> that hath been ſo much your Enemy, and which you ought to value, for being true to its Principle (if that be ſtill a Vertue with you) I am told is far from be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing averſe, from improving, as well as im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bracing ſo fair an Opportunity and Advantage.</p>
            <p>This is written out of meer good will to you; be not ſo barbarous as to gueſs the Author, to his Prejudice; gueſs his meaning, if you can; he wiſhes as well to you, as he does to all his deareſt Intereſts upon Earth; and hath, on purpoſe, avoided all the Beauties of Language, and every ſpecious Ratiocination, that his Stile and his Repreſentations might be as plain as his Heart, which he aſſures you is</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>Yours,</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
